[Music]
Thomas thank you very much for joining
me you're a writer with for many places
including New York Times Magazine
Harper's and you've also written a book
called unlearning race and I'd love to
talk to you about kind of the current
cultural situation and also I think may
be the place to start is the unlearning
race now while you've got books like
white fragility at the top of the charts
and how to be an anti-racist seems
countercultural almost or it's it's it's
not the current understanding of what
the where the discussion is at right now
what are you making of the the current
kind of situation the current situation
is a complicated one on the one hand it
is heartening to see such interest being
paid to questions of how race is
constructed how it's enforced imposed
how it governs our lives in our society
this is all to the good but as you point
out the main books the texts that are
being quoted and cited everywhere are
texts that I do take issue with because
they in many ways Rhian scribe ideas of
racial essentialism that my book is
arguing I guess and that I'm trying to
get the conversation to look past so you
have a book like white fragility by
Robyn D'Angelo which is the big
bestseller right now and it's
problematic in certain ways because it
it presents white people as an
undifferentiated mass not as individuals
with agency and it presents blacks in a
way that's quite troubling to me as kind
of like an undifferentiated mass of
people who are fundamentally oppressed
and can only ever react to the real
agents of history who are or whites who
are also paradoxically not individuals
and then on the other hand you have
eeprom candy and some others who you
know they make very persuasive and good
calls for Franta racism but
kind of enforce another kind of
essentialism that sees people as
fundamentally black and fundamentally
white and my argument is it's not
necessarily at odds with candies how to
be in an anti-racist but it doesn't stop
at the notion that you have to be an
anti-racist and I think we have to do
two things at the same time we have to
on the one hand fight racism which is
real which governs our lives but we also
have to always keep our eye on the
ultimate objective which would be to do
away with the categories of race that
racism imposes I start from the premise
that racism creates race and not the
other way around yeah I think as you're
saying like you have to balance these
things at the same time that seems to be
a very difficult conversation to have
right now because it's very nuanced for
example Brett Weinstein put out a piece
talking about
he's an evolutionary biologist and said
that talking about race is very can be
very dangerous because it essentially
triggers some very deep evolutionary
drives it enforces tribalism so how can
you have that conversation while at the
same time recognizing that there is
deep-rooted inequality there are
legacies of oppression and holding that
both of those at the same time but not
reimposing kind of these essential
categories but that feels like a very
delicate balancing act it is quite a
delicate balancing balancing act and I
think that part of the thing that we're
seeing now is that not everybody is
necessarily interested in making the
effort to balance so part of what has to
happen is that people have to come as
good faith interlocutors into the
exchange there is quite you know that
I'm not I wouldn't say that that's not
out there but it seems to me that
there's kind of less of an appetite for
that now than there was certainly in
2008 when the nation seemed to be like
in a good faith way fundamentally
inspired by the idea that maybe we could
transcend this kind of historical sin
that defines our country and of course
you know that kind of euphoria was very
short-lived
we soon saw the limits of the symbolic
victory of having a mixed-race black man
the foot mixed racing quotes at the helm
of the government and now it seems that
the the disappointment was such that
there's less and less of a generosity
and willingness for people even on the
left to to give up these categories I
feel like oftentimes it's a very lonely
place to be saying that the ultimate
goal still has to be to transcend racial
categories because they don't
biologically exist in meaningful ways
that's not something that everybody
agrees with anymore and I remember very
well in 2008 that would be something
that people would say why is the
ultimate goal so it's tricky and not you
know and some of it has to do with the
fact that they're making inroads people
are making progress by reunifying these
categories by by doubling down on them
it's it's it's it's working it's getting
it's getting people to concede quite a
lot so it's tough to tell people that
this thing that's working in a pragmatic
sense is something that doesn't work in
a philosophical or maybe even moral or
ethical sense and you should actually
give it up all might have long-term
consequences that are going to be
dangerous victories and gains might be
Pyrrhic in nature yeah I'm interested in
your journey through this but how did
you become particularly interested and
how where have you ended up in your kind
of explorations of this topic so my
journey on race has always been somewhat
out of the mainstream because I'm 39
years old I was born in 1981 I'm the son
of a black man from the segregated south
my father's actually from Galveston
Texas it's June 19th today which is
Juneteenth
which is the traditional holiday because
slaves in Galveston were free at about
two years after everybody else and so
when they got the news that they were
freed they ran into the streets and
rejoice that's Juneteenth so my father
comes from that world he was born in
1937 fully became an adult before civil
rights my mother is a white woman from
San Diego California and
my brother and I were raised in look to
others as a multiracial family but we
were raised by both of our parents I
said we were a black family my mother
was white but we were not raised as
biracial we were we were regarded as
black by the black kids and the white
kids that we knew and her parents raised
us to be black and we accepted that and
it wasn't a very complicated
relationship to identity that I grew up
with in New Jersey and it wasn't until I
was in my late 20s early 30s when I
married a white woman from France moved
to Paris and found myself more and more
in conversations where I was trying to
explain the logic of the one-drop rule
which governed my own sense of self back
in the States but which Europeans don't
necessarily assume and aren't
necessarily even familiar with so when
people would ask me you know in France
the question is often what are your
origins and that means because the
French don't necessarily speak about
race as such that means what are you and
so I would say I'm black and that would
often draw kind of surprised that it
doesn't draw back in the States and then
I'd get into these conversations and I
found myself defending this logic of
hypo dissent in the one-drop rule which
is really the logic of the plantation
and and and I found myself less and less
convinced by it the more I spent time
out of the United States but I couldn't
quite get myself to give up on it in
2012 I wrote an op-ed in the New York
Times arguing that no matter what my
wife my wife and my children would look
like they would be black because black
is a as a choice and it's a discipline
and it's a kind of it's a moral stance
and I kind of really realized that I was
writing that op-ed to convince an
audience of one which was myself it was
difficult for me to break with this kind
of construction constructed I identity
that that had always been just my
reflexive understanding of myself but
when my daughter Marla was actually born
in 2013 her physical presence in my life
suddenly thrust when I guess I would
call the fiction of race before me in a
way that my
mixed background never had and it wasn't
the realization that I here I had a
white daughter with blonde hair and blue
eyes and then white skin it was that I
fundamentally don't believe that you can
be a different race than your child or
that you can be a different race than
your parent I didn't see a white child
there I just saw if I can have a
daughter like this what did what does it
even mean for me to be a black man and
what does it mean for her to be walking
into the world presumed to be white if
she can be directly descended from black
slaves so then that began began the
process of what became the book
self-portrait in black and white I'm
learning race yeah I I wonder whether
it's also a generational thing
because I I was brought up by very
racially aware anti-racist left-wing
parents and I can remember back then I'm
confused like I I don't really
understand the world we're in now
because it seems that for example I
remember being brought up and being told
why the word colored was no longer
okayed in the 1980s and now we've kind
of ended up in this place where people
of color seems to be the accepted
definition and I remembered like even as
a even an eight or nine or ten year old
understanding or at least understood I
thought I understood at the time that it
was inherently other ring to have a word
that sort of meant them an ass and now
suddenly we've ended up in this place
where there seems to be another kind of
I I'm confused and I think a lot of
people kind of white liberals like
myself feel very yeah I'm sure and and
and quite scared in some ways to say
certain things now because they're a
certain it seems that that there is a
certain there is a certain set of
actions in a certain set of ways of
talking about this that is the accepted
wisdom rather than what I what I used to
understand is kind of being anti-racist
there's the accepted wisdom but it had
accepted accepted wisdom is also rapidly
shifting all the time
you're constantly having to rearrange
the way you think about language and the
way you think about referring to other
groups of people people of color is the
term that really bothers me on several
levels first of all it's extraordinarily
on precise nine-tenths of the world or
more fits into that definition because
only a tiny fraction of humanity is
European or European descended and it
seems to take this nine-tenths of
humanity and define them like solely
having this thing in common which is
their mistreatment by white people
that's the only thing that would link
elect inna a black person a Chinese
person in the American discourse that
seeks to put them together as people of
color so it's it's it's it's a way it's
a kind of back door right back into
white supremacy by other means if you
think about it freer in a second it
still it separates people into whites
and non-whites and the relation is one
of domination and hierarchy and that's
what I'm trying to get past but the
language itself the terms are shifting I
mean just this week the conversation is
about now more and more publications
will be pub will be capitalizing the
letter B and black but will not be
capitalizing white so every group will
be capitalized but only one group will
not be capitalized and they'll be white
people who will understand that they are
still the center of everybody else's
drama and story yeah that they're the
default in some way yes I've seen even
in the last two weeks a lot of friends
on Facebook for example posting POC pot
and asking questions like does anyone
know any good POC facilitators yeah
and it's for me that feels incredibly
dehumanizing so to see this language
come in full force in the last couple of
weeks in a way that for me feels deep I
would never use it because I feel that
is dehumanizing to call someone a POC
for me is is really I don't know I'm in
this strange world I see this sort of
strange world grow
around me I don't I don't know how to
navigate it I'm confused
you know it's dehumanizing also to think
that my view is only valuable or wanted
or necessary because I'm a POC the world
that I want to create in that we were
supposed to be moving towards a world
where views are valid or not valid based
on their intrinsic merit that all people
are welcome and not discriminated
against based on their characteristics
beyond their control
and that this is how we kind of like
orient the public sphere but the idea
you know my wife sent me a tweet
yesterday that was a screenshot of a
restaurant owners email she had been
contacted for an interview with a
newspaper and her response was we're an
all white owned establishment and so my
my new policy is that I need to know if
you are also interviewing POC restaurant
owners and if not and I want to give up
my slot in the article so you can talk
to a POC it seems on the one hand like
what she's doing is generous and
correcting a kind of exclusion that's
going on but if you stop to think about
it for even a second this is this is
crazy and it's Rhian scribing a racial
essentialism it has nothing to do with
the restaurant just go ahead and find
POC it doesn't matter what the person is
it doesn't matter if the person's now
Asian it doesn't matter if the person's
Filipino it doesn't matter if they're
light in it this is all interchangeable
I'm a white person I have privilege so
let me give up my seat to anybody
regardless of what they have to say or
if it's even relevant to your story so
just the idea that what we're doing the
world that we're in the process of
hastily creating is when the Rhian
scribes race is the only category that
matters and that cannot be transcended
is a dangerous place to be going back to
regardless of whether we're there from
malicious intent or from well-meaning
stumbles that we're making along the way
and it's and it's worse than that
because it's not just a world where race
is primary it's also
a certain particular type of opinion
within that category is primary as well
or within the minority is
deracinated you're not actually you're
an artificial Indian or an artificial
black man if you don't you're an
artificial gay man if you don't Buddha
judge for example was called actually
the first straight gay candidate for
president because he wasn't an authentic
daemon because his views disqualified
him from having that voice we've seen
Ayane Presley the representative member
of the squad with Alexandria of Casio
courtesan Elan Omar
she talked about we no longer want to
have black and brown faces without black
and brown voices this gets dangerous
this this this is how you quash healthy
disagreement and this is how you quash
and squash the ability for people to to
challenge orthodoxies that may or may
not be actually held by the majority
whatever group you're claiming to speak
speak on behalf of yeah and I've not
spoken publicly on any of these topics
before but I was listening to the the
Sam Harris podcast the other day and I
thought he made a really good point
which was I could have got on Glenn
Lowry to talk about this I could have
got on Coleman Hughes I'm really
interested in talking to you because
you've got a background in thinking very
hard about these issues to explore in
conversation with but the idea that we
can't talk about certain things if we're
not from that background is part seems
to be part of the problem
well absolutely that's how you you
preclude the possibility of dialogue
that's what the idea that there's what
Glenn Lowry calls and what I'm very
convinced is a real problem in today's
discourse is this idea of identity
epistemology that because I am black I
have access to some kind of knowledge
that you can never possess so the only
thing that you can do is you can be
quiet and listen and be an ally but the
only way that you can the only authentic
ally ship is silence
that's not you we all know that that
can't possibly hold that can't work
that's that's that's not how you build a
multi-ethnic society that works and you
know there's a backlash dirt like we
talked in the beginning of unforeseen
consequences to short-term power grabs
this is partially I don't want to say
it's the only reason but this is
partially how we did end up with someone
like Trump resonating so wildly we're
creating a society where everybody has
an identity that gives them a knowledge
and a morality we're moving towards
identity morality identity ethics so
everybody can be proud of their identity
and it gives them some special insight
into the human condition except for one
group and that one group is the the
group that's historically been in power
and that is aware that it's
demographically shrinking so what does
that set up that sets up a situation
where that group is going to sum up
members of that group we're going to
fight like hell to to react in the worst
possible ways to this new world that
clearly singles them out and punishes
them so this is where we are in this
horrific Lee polarized society with
Donald Trump as our president
representing this embattled my
soon-to-be minority yeah I might be
really interested in your thoughts on
this topic as a writer because that type
of kind of epistemology seems to be the
death of art primarily because it's the
death of empathy it's the death of like
I I know that you were heavily
influenced by hip hop culture growing up
as was I some my favorite albums of all
time most deaths black on both sides oh
wow really Kendrick Lamar I was obsessed
with Kendrick Lamar from kind of good
kid maad city onwards for me those kind
of artists and the the way they talked
about the black experience and also the
the kind of the liberation of the black
experience that's that's a huge value to
humanity that's that's a huge value to
all of us and this sort of sense of the
sense of epistemology that kind of ties
in to like the whole idea of cultural
appropriation
creation just seems like it walls us off
from each other in a way that seems
incredibly dangerous and damaging
absolutely I mean the way that we've
made such games you could argue is
through the I mean I have criticisms of
what the representation of authentic
blackness through hip-hop culture
through the mainstream hip-hop culture
that was sold to us in the 90s and early
2000s of criticism what that did to the
image that we bought of ourselves but
also it would be impossible to argue
that the world's embrace of hip-hop
music and culture hasn't done as much or
more to humanize blacks in the eyes of
the rest of the world best done more
that in some professional sports have
done an enormous amount of work that
even the civil rights movement couldn't
fully attain it made people fall in love
with the culture and the people who made
it so art is has a way of communicating
that politics never can that polemics
never can that you know you can make you
can you can read a novel and have an
understanding of something going on that
you just won't get from an op-ed no
matter what so the idea that now we're
shutting that down I mean there was just
this argument that this part Porto Rican
woman who wrote American dirt which
Oprah's Book Club picked last fall this
big bestseller that dealt with like an
important moral issue of our time which
is you know immigration on the southern
border this woman wrote a novel about it
and she brought a huge amount of readers
to this subject and readers who might
not have approached the subject
otherwise and she was essentially
dressed down and told that she couldn't
do this and I think that we're heading
into a very dangerous place where
everybody doesn't just not have access
to the whole human story and access to
each other's stories but everybody can
only write their own very narrow nose
busted specific story which is a way of
segregating ideas and experiences so I
can only ever talk to you about my black
identity but I
never talked to you about apparently I
can never talk to you about my love
knowledge of French literature or art or
food culture I don't know if I have the
right to wear the name Thomas Chatterton
who's who was a great poet from Bristol
that's cert that's not do I have a claim
to that am I supposed to be silent on
that we're getting into a dangerous
place but the the way that it works in
fact is that everybody actually can
basically do things except for except
for again white people white people
can't because there's some understood
power relation and white people using
other people's stories so I think that
what we have to do and what's difficult
to do is just have principles and values
that apply equally to everybody and not
have these kind of cabinets that always
try to seek to address in very imprecise
ways historical power imbalances because
the problem with this type of correction
is that we see all too often were over
correcting in ways that invite
unforeseen consequences and that make it
impossible to talk to each other and
understand each other hmm I yeah I
wanted to return to what you just said
about hip-hop culture because that's
what I love about most death I'm I
remember his in he's got a song called
hip hop that I think is one of the
greatest love kind of letters to the art
and he says in that hip hop is
prosecution evidence and out-of-court
settlement ad space for liquor which is
so so hip hop is also critical of itself
like the greatest hip hop is also self
reflective and critical and and the
other side of it as well that I find
very disconcerting with the current a
lot of the current dynamics is that it
makes an another most death line where
he talks about Invisible Man got the
whole world watching like a black
culture has been probably the driving
force of American culture and American
from Elvis Presley onwards and how much
it's been kind of yeah how much it was
appropriated by by by white artists as
well but but it's so intertwined with
with how we think of America and the
driving force of America probably one of
the the main driving forces of America
and what seems very disturbing about the
and framing of only seeing black people
as as victims seems to exclude that and
actually like there's so much to be
inspired by proud of and amazed by in in
in that in black culture I agree 100%
I mean that's the kind of black southern
tradition my father comes from and that
seems very normal and natural to me you
don't think of yourself as a victim this
is a group of people you know Ralph
Ellison called blackness a kind of
discipline and that resonates with me
very deeply I've always been very proud
to be I guess part of a culture and a
tradition that that achieved
extraordinary artistic in and global
contributions that survived that didn't
just survive but survive with a blues
sensibility that was a kind of Stoicism
and a kind of taking the worst that a
life gave you and flipping it with a
little bit of style and with a bit of
swag and turning it into something that
actually yet people sitting in Paris
wanted to hear Louis Armstrong he's
taking American pain and flipping it
this is something to be proud of and
there's no people in the world that
doesn't have a history of pain and
exploitation
it depends at what point in time you
catch them in this you know in the
struggle but I have always been proud to
be black I've never seen it as something
that was akin to a disability which is
the way and I don't mean to act and
actually I don't want to get in trouble
for saying something that sounds ablest
or anything like that I simply mean that
I never thought of being black as
something other than a form of strength
and discipline and a way of
understanding America that maybe gave me
access to a truth about America James
Baldwin has spoken and written very
eloquently about there being something
quite monstrous about getting to the age
of 40 and never having actually know
paying and never having actually lost
something and never having struggled and
then and then something happens to you
later in life and you can't take it and
you this is how he described a certain
type of whiteness that operates in
society you know a certain type of
innocence and I never won a better
aspire to that so I I have a tough time
with the privileged conversation because
I don't think that some of the insights
into human life and nature that coming
up in a black tradition exposed me to I
don't think of it as being as lacking
and privileged in fact I think of that
as something that's helped me grow to
almost the age of 40 in a way that I'm
proud of and and how do you hold that
tension because you your books called
unlearning race but you're we're also
talking about the value of black culture
black America is a distinct thing in
itself this is there not a paradox there
I don't think so I think that if you can
vary and a lot of people when they when
sometimes I give talks and I see that
some people in the audience who define
themselves as black they they're open to
the idea of moving past race but it
hurts a little bit to think of severing
ties with a group of people they want to
express solidarity with which is
something completely understandable but
I think it's very different to say race
isn't real
there's nothing about blood and skin
that we're talking about we're talking
about belonging to a community of people
a tradition a certain region regionalism
matters you know being black in America
is not the same as being quote unquote
black in Jamaica or you know anywhere
else so you can belong to these people
but we also have to find different ways
of belonging to people who don't come
from this community or a tradition we
have to rethink what makes us Americans
what makes us humans what makes us
citizens of the 21st century I think
that holding on to blackness as a
culture is it is as healthy as holding
on to Italian this is a culture a Jewish
this isn't as a religion and a culture
but it but we're all and it almost gets
to the point where people would laugh at
you for pointing this out but what we
are is were members of the human race I
mean you have to have both a more
general understanding of yourself
we're just members of the human race and
a much more specific understanding of
yourself I'm a British guy from
Yorkshire
I'm you know my mother's side comes from
from Vienna and my father's side comes
from Sicily that's that's where my
people come from but before that they
came from another place I mean it's it's
a big it is it's actually hard to ask
people to speak about themselves this
way because we want these kind of easy
monolithic color labels to slap on to
extremely diverse experiences and just
to make it easy for us to categorize
ourselves but I think that we have to
achieve a perspective that goes beyond
that if we're ever gonna get past this
kind of balkanized
debate that's paralyzing our society but
when I was sort of doing a little bit of
research before this conversation and I
read an article in The New York Review
of Books where you were put together
with I think people like Glenn Lowry
John Atwater and described it as black
conservatives which didn't seem which
which didn't seem right I'll get your
reaction to that right like the AVL a.rb
what do you make of that
characterization I mean it's it's lazy
it it bothers me because I defined
myself as a liberal have always
certainly voted that way find no home in
the Republican Party whatsoever
perhaps if the writer was implying that
there are elements of cultural
conservatism and in there maybe that's
the case maybe maybe I don't
I guess maybe yeah if conserving
elements of the past makes sense maybe
he was implying that we're conservative
in the way that Ralph Ellison can be
called conservative conservative
personality or something like this but
it's also kind of slanderous and it's
used as an epithet when when another by
writer
you're conservative if you don't
identify that way it's a way of dealing
jet amaizing any kind of heterodox
aspects of your views that that don't go
with the kind of woke left or good
orthodoxy that carries the day right now
so yeah it bothers me quite a bit and as
far as I'm aware John McWhorter Coleman
Hughes Glenn Lowry any of those guys
that I routinely get lumped with none of
them defined themselves as conservative
I think only Glenn Lowry did in the 90s
but he since you know he redefined
himself so it's you know it's just
something that you know it's a label
that I reject and I try to argue back
against yeah I mean I was struck like it
it struck me as very odd I mean it was I
would describe you all as heterodox
thinkers but certainly not conservative
and it felt like a way of kind of
policing the conversation in terms of
what views are allowed within kind of
liberal the liberal world and which are
not and I find that really really
interesting as a phenomenon because
there's this kind of paradox that only
one particular perspective is allowed if
you're from a certain minority group and
that that seems essentialist at its core
that the sort of paradox of that seems
incredibly dehumanizing and a real
paradox of of the way that the left can
think about race at times yeah and it's
not just other so-called blacks who will
level that at you if you look I don't
know I mean the new cycle moves so fast
but recently Joe Biden in an interview
with a black interlocutor made an
off-the-cuff remark like the interviewer
was asking him for more time to asked
and more questions to go back to his
community with to make the case for
voting for Joe Biden and Joe Biden's
response was well you just tell them if
you gotta make up your mind about
whether for me or the other guy you
ain't really black it's just it's
mind-blowing it's extraordinarily
patronizing and it kind of treats
yeah it treats
it makes an essential Azamat of what
should actually be
something far more complicated of course
I understand that like yeah most black
nine out of ten black people won't ever
vote for Donald Trump over Joe Biden I
certainly won't even after he said that
but the idea that you must think a
certain way in order to be authentically
yourself as a member of this community
is really I think it's destructive but
it's also concerning that on the other
side you have people like Candice Owens
using that as a as a way of divide being
more divisive like that that in some
ways is far more concerning when you see
that kind of that that truth kind of
weaponized on the other side is in a
very divisive way you mean Kenda so in
somebody who's just sabotaging the
conversation for her own personal game
yeah I mean I see her being very very
divisive I mean she's she has elements
of truth in some of what she's saying
but she's using in a very political
politically charged way to to argue for
black people to vote Trump to vote
Republican well yeah I just don't take
someone like Candace Owens as a
good-faith conversation partner so I
think that it is very important to
[Music]
I think it's important to think through
who is actually coming into the debate
in a good-faith way and so something
like canvas Owens is kind of a
non-starter she's done so much that's so
sensational it's kind of a non-starter
but to dismiss someone like who we've
been talking about like Glander or John
it's not authentically representing a
black position because they diverged
from the orthodoxy is something else
altogether I think it's really important
and that's what kind of the problem is
with Candis Owens because she inserts
herself into the debate and then people
can lump her with a guy who's a serious
guy like John McWhorter and and then you
know this the whole conversation breaks
down so why do you think things have
shifted in this direction what's your
sense of why we've moved in this
direction since 2008 I think that there
is real profound and in many ways
justified disappointment with the limits
of what actually happened I think that
certainly there's extraordinary
disappointment with the idea that
someone no matter what your politics are
someone is elegant and is fundamentally
you know trying to do what he believes
is right someone who was trying to unify
the nation somebody like Barack Obama
could be followed by someone like Donald
Trump who appeals to the most divisive
aspects of the American discourse who
really it's an insult to follow brock
obama by donald trump and there's
there's really no way around that so I
think that that exacerbated things quite
a bit I think you can't talk about any
of this without talking about the impact
of social media on all of our lives and
the kind of incentives that dopamine
driven incentives that you know drive
our politics of recrimination and you
know the break us into warring tribes
following politics as a sport the kind
of self-righteous witch-hunt that goes
down to find somebody who's transgressed
and then shame them on social media you
know and then you're kind of
rediscovering your tribal identity makes
me in turn rediscover mine and my travel
feelings intensify so we and
see everything all the time now and
we're always in conversation about
everything all the time
so all of these factors come into play
at the same time and I think that we're
trying to figure out how to make our
culture's our societies our world work
when were exposed to each other and each
other's flaws and each other's
limitations more than we've ever been in
the past Thomas thank you very much it's
a really interesting conversation I'm
really really glad that you agreed to do
it thanks for having me
rebel wisdom was set up to make sense of
the world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense-making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom Jim a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching see you
soon